<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter>
<title>CoffeeScript Syntax</title>
 
  
  <para>
    Firstly, before we get any further into this section, I want to
    reiterate that while CoffeeScript's syntax is often identical with
    JavaScript's, it's not a superset, and therefore some JavaScript
    keywords, such as <literal>function</literal> and
    <literal>var</literal>, aren't permitted, and will throw syntax
    errors. If you're writing a CoffeeScript file, it needs to be pure
    CoffeeScript; you can't intermingle the two languages.
  </para>
  <para>
    Why isn't CoffeeScript a superset? Well, the very fact that
    whitespace is significant in CoffeeScript programs prevents it being
    a superset. And, once that decision's been made, the team decided
    you might as well go the full hog and deprecate some JavaScript
    keywords and features in the name of simplicity and in an effort to
    reduce many commonly occurring bugs.
  </para>
  <para>
    What I find mind-blowing, in a meta sort of way, is that the
    CoffeeScript interpreter itself is actually written in CoffeeScript.
    It looks like the chicken or egg paradox has finally been solved!
  </para>
  <para>
    Right, so firstly let's tackle the basic stuff. There are no
    semicolons in CoffeeScript, it'll add them automatically for you
    upon compilation. Semicolons were the cause of much debate in the
    JavaScript community, and behind some weird interpreter
    <ulink url="http://bonsaiden.github.com/JavaScript-Garden/#core.semicolon">behavior</ulink>.
    Anyway, CoffeeScript resolves this problem for you by simply
    removing semi-colons from its syntax, adding them as needed behind
    the scenes.
  </para>
  <para>
    Comments are in the same format as Ruby comments, starting with a
    hash character.
  </para>
  <screen>
# A comment
</screen>
  <para>
    Multiline comments are also supported, and are brought forward to
    the generated JavaScript. They're enclosed by three hash characters.
  </para>
  <screen>
###
  A multiline comment, perhaps a LICENSE.
###
</screen><para>Compiles down to:</para><screen>
  /*
    A multiline comment, perhaps a LICENSE.
  */


</screen>
  <para>
    As I briefly alluded to, whitespace is significant in CoffeeScript.
    In practice, this means that you can replace curly brackets
    (<literal>{}</literal>) with a tab. This takes inspiration from
    Python's syntax, and has the excellent side effect of ensuring that
    your script is formatted in a sane manner, otherwise it won't even
    compile!
  </para>
  <sect1>
    <title>Variables &amp; Scope</title>
    <para>
      CoffeeScript fixes one of the major bugbears with JavaScript,
      global variables. In JavaScript, it's all too easy to accidentally
      declare a global variable by forgetting to include
      <literal>var</literal> before the variable assignment.
      CoffeeScript solves this by simply removing global variables.
      Behind the scenes, CoffeeScript wraps up scripts with an anonymous
      function, keeping the local context, and automatically prefixes
      all variable assignments with <literal>var</literal>. For example,
      take this simple variable assignment in CoffeeScript:
    </para>
    <screen>
myVariable = "test"
</screen><para>Compiles down to:</para><screen>(function() {
  var myVariable;

  myVariable = "test";

}).call(this);
</screen>
    <para>
      As you can see, the variable assignment is kept completely local,
      it's impossible to accidentally create a global variable.
      CoffeeScript actually takes this a step further, and makes it
      difficult to shadow a higher-level variable. This goes a great
      deal to prevent some of the most common mistakes developers make
      in JavaScript.
    </para>
    <para>
      However, sometimes it's useful to create global variables. You can
      either do this by directly setting them as properties on the
      global object (<literal>window</literal> in browsers), or with the
      following pattern:
    </para>
    <screen>
exports = this
exports.MyVariable = "foo-bar"
</screen><para>Compiles down to:</para><screen>(function() {
  var exports;

  exports = this;

  exports.MyVariable = "foo-bar";

}).call(this);
</screen>
    <para>
      In the root context, <literal>this</literal> is equal to the
      global object, and by creating a local <literal>exports</literal>
      variable you're making it really obvious to anyone reading your
      code exactly which global variables a script is creating.
      Additionally, it paves the way for CommonJS modules, which we're
      going to cover later in the book.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Functions</title>
    <para>
      CoffeeScript removes the rather verbose
      <literal>function</literal> statement, and replaces it with a thin
      arrow: <literal>-&gt;</literal>. Functions can be one liners or
      indented on multiple lines. The last expression in the function is
      implicitly returned. In other words, you don't need to use the
      <literal>return</literal> statement unless you want to return
      earlier inside the function.
    </para>
    <para>
      With that in mind, let's take a look at an example:
    </para>
    <screen>
func = -&gt; "bar"
</screen><para>Compiles down to:</para><screen>(function() {
  var func;

  func = function() {
    return "bar";
  };

}).call(this);
</screen>
    <para>
      You can see in the resultant compilation, the
      <literal>-&gt;</literal> is turned into a
      <literal>function</literal> statement, and the
      <literal>"bar"</literal> string is automatically
      returned.
    </para>
    <para>
      As mentioned earlier, there's no reason why we can't use multiple
      lines, as long as we indent the function body properly.
    </para>
    <screen>
func = -&gt;
  # An extra line
  "bar"
</screen><para>Compiles down to:</para><screen>(function() {
  var func;

  func = function() {
    return "bar";
  };

}).call(this);
</screen>
    <sect2>
      <title>Function arguments</title>
      <para>
        How about specifying arguments? Well, CoffeeScript lets you do
        that by specifying arguments in parentheses before the arrow.
      </para>
      <screen>
times = (a, b) -&gt; a * b
</screen><para>Compiles down to:</para><screen>(function() {
  var times;

  times = function(a, b) {
    return a * b;
  };

}).call(this);
</screen>
      <para>
        CoffeeScript supports default arguments too, for example:
      </para>
      <screen>
times = (a = 1, b = 2) -&gt; a * b
</screen><para>Compiles down to:</para><screen>(function() {
  var times;

  times = function(a, b) {
    if (a == null) a = 1;
    if (b == null) b = 2;
    return a * b;
  };

}).call(this);
</screen>
      <para>
        You can also use splats to accept multiple arguments, denoted by
        <literal>...</literal>
      </para>
      <screen>
sum = (nums...) -&gt; 
  result = 0
  nums.forEach (n) -&gt; result += n
  result
</screen><para>Compiles down to:</para><screen>(function() {
  var sum;
  var __slice = Array.prototype.slice;

  sum = function() {
    var nums, result;
    nums = 1 &lt;= arguments.length ? __slice.call(arguments, 0) : [];
    result = 0;
    nums.forEach(function(n) {
      return result += n;
    });
    return result;
  };

}).call(this);
</screen>
      <para>
        In the example above, <literal>nums</literal> is an array of all
        the arguments passed to the function. It's not an
        <literal>arguments</literal> object, but rather a real array, so
        you don't need to concern yourself with
        <literal>Array.prototype.splice</literal> or
        <literal>jQuery.makeArray()</literal> if you want to manipulate
        it.
      </para>
      <screen>
trigger = (events...) -&gt;
  events.splice(1, 0, this)
  this.constructor.trigger.apply(events)
</screen><para>Compiles down to:</para><screen>(function() {
  var trigger;
  var __slice = Array.prototype.slice;

  trigger = function() {
    var events;
    events = 1 &lt;= arguments.length ? __slice.call(arguments, 0) : [];
    events.splice(1, 0, this);
    return this.constructor.trigger.apply(events);
  };

}).call(this);
</screen>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Function invocation</title>
      <para>
        Functions can be invoked exactly as in JavaScript, with parens
        <literal>()</literal>, <literal>apply()</literal> or
        <literal>call()</literal>. However, like Ruby, CoffeeScript will
        automatically call functions if they are invoked with at least
        one argument.
      </para>
      <screen>
a = "Howdy!"

alert a
# Equivalent to:
alert(a)

alert inspect a
# Equivalent to:
alert(inspect(a))
</screen><para>Compiles down to:</para><screen>(function() {
  var a;

  a = "Howdy!";

  alert(a);

  alert(a);

  alert(inspect(a));

  alert(inspect(a));

}).call(this);
</screen>
      <para>
        Although parenthesis is optional, I'd recommend using it if it's
        not immediately obvious what's being invoked, and with which
        arguments. In the last example, with <literal>inspect</literal>,
        I'd definitely recommend wrapping at least the
        <literal>inspect</literal> invocation in parens.
      </para>
      <screen>
alert inspect(a)
</screen><para>Compiles down to:</para><screen>
  alert(inspect(a));
</screen>
      <para>
        If you don't pass any arguments with an invocation, CoffeeScript
        has no way of working out if you intend to invoke the function,
        or just treat it like a variable. In this respect,
        CoffeeScript's behavior differs from Ruby which always invokes
        references to functions, and is more similar to Python's. This
        has been the source of a few errors in my CoffeeScript programs,
        so it's worth keeping an eye out for cases where you intend to
        call a function without any arguments, and include parenthesis.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Function context</title>
      <para>
        Context changes are rife within JavaScript, especially with
        event callbacks, so CoffeeScript provides a few helpers to
        manage this. One such helper is a variation on
        <literal>-&gt;</literal>, the fat arrow function:
        <literal>=&gt;</literal>
      </para>
      <para>
        Using the fat arrow instead of the thin arrow ensures that the
        function context will be bound to the local one. For example:
      </para>
      <screen>
this.clickHandler = -&gt; alert "clicked"
element.addEventListener "click", (e) =&gt; this.clickHandler(e)
</screen><para>Compiles down to:</para><screen>(function() {
  var _this = this;

  this.clickHandler = function() {
    return alert("clicked");
  };

  element.addEventListener("click", function(e) {
    return _this.clickHandler(e);
  });

}).call(this);
</screen>
      <para>
        The reason you might want to do this is that callbacks from
        <literal>addEventListener()</literal> are executed in the
        context of the <literal>element</literal>, i.e.
        <literal>this</literal> equals the element. If you want to keep
        <literal>this</literal> equal to the local context, without
        doing a <literal>self = this</literal> dance, fat arrows are the
        way to go.
      </para>
      <para>
        This binding idea is a similar concept to jQuery's
        <ulink url="http://api.jquery.com/jQuery.proxy/"><literal>proxy()</literal></ulink>
        or
        <ulink url="https://developer.mozilla.org/en/JavaScript/Reference/Global_Objects/Function/bind">ES5's</ulink>
        <literal>bind()</literal> functions.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Object literals &amp; array definition</title>
    <para>
      Object literals can be specified exactly as in JavaScript, with a
      pair of braces and key/value statements. However, like with
      function invocation, CoffeeScript makes the braces optional. In
      fact, you can also use indentation and new lines instead of comma
      separation.
    </para>
    <screen>
object1 = {one: 1, two: 2}

# Without braces
object2 = one: 1, two: 2

# Using new lines instead of commas
object3 = 
  one: 1
  two: 2

User.create(name: "John Smith")
</screen><para>Compiles down to:</para><screen>(function() {
  var object1, object2, object3;

  object1 = {
    one: 1,
    two: 2
  };

  object2 = {
    one: 1,
    two: 2
  };

  object3 = {
    one: 1,
    two: 2
  };

  User.create({
    name: "John Smith"
  });

}).call(this);
</screen>
    <para>
      Likewise, arrays can use whitespace instead of comma separators,
      although the square brackets (<literal>[]</literal>) are still
      required.
    </para>
    <screen>
array1 = [1, 2, 3]

array2 = [
  1
  2
  3
]

array3 = [1,2,3,]
</screen><para>Compiles down to:</para><screen>(function() {
  var array1, array2, array3;

  array1 = [1, 2, 3];

  array2 = [1, 2, 3];

  array3 = [1, 2, 3];

}).call(this);
</screen>
    <para>
      As you can see in the example above, CoffeeScript has also
      stripped the trailing comma in <literal>array3</literal>, another
      common source of cross-browser errors.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Flow control</title>
    <para>
      The convention of optional parentheses continues with
      CoffeeScript's <literal>if</literal> and <literal>else</literal>
      keywords.
    </para>
    <screen>
if true == true
  "We're ok"

if true != true then "Panic"

# Equivalent to:
#  (1 &gt; 0) ? "Ok" : "Y2K!"
if 1 &gt; 0 then "Ok" else "Y2K!"
</screen><para>Compiles down to:</para><screen>
  if (true === true) "We're ok";

  if (true !== true) "Panic";

  if (1 &gt; 0) {
    "Ok";
  } else {
    "Y2K!";
  }
</screen>
    <para>
      As you can see above, if the <literal>if</literal> statement is on
      one line, you'll need to use the <literal>then</literal> keyword,
      so CoffeeScript knows when the block begins. Conditional operators
      (<literal>?:</literal>) are not supported, instead you should use
      a single line <literal>if/else</literal> statement.
    </para>
    <para>
      CoffeeScript also includes a Ruby idiom of allowing suffixed
      <literal>if</literal> statements.
    </para>
    <screen>
alert "It's cold!" if heat &lt; 5
</screen><para>Compiles down to:</para><screen>
  if (heat &lt; 5) alert("It's cold!");
</screen>
    <para>
      Instead of using the exclamation mark (<literal>!</literal>) for
      negation, you can also use the <literal>not</literal> keyword -
      which can sometimes make your code more readable as exclamation
      marks can be easy to miss.
    </para>
    <screen>
if not true then "Panic"
</screen><para>Compiles down to:</para><screen>
  if (!true) "Panic";
</screen>
    <para>
      In the example above, we could also use the CoffeeScript's
      <literal>unless</literal> statement, the opposite of
      <literal>if</literal>.
    </para>
    <screen>
unless true
  "Panic"
</screen><para>Compiles down to:</para><screen>
  if (!true) "Panic";
</screen>
    <para>
      In a similar fashion to <literal>not</literal>, CoffeeScript also
      introduces the <literal>is</literal> statement, which translates
      to <literal>===</literal>.
    </para>
    <screen>
if true is 1
  "Type coercion fail!"
</screen><para>Compiles down to:</para><screen>
  if (true === 1) "Type coercion fail!";
</screen>
    <para>
      As an alternative to <literal>is not</literal>, you can use
      <literal>isnt</literal>.
    </para>
    <screen>
if true isnt true
  alert "Opposite day!"
</screen>
    <para>
      You may have noticed in the examples above, that CoffeeScript is
      converting <literal>==</literal> operators into
      <literal>===</literal> and <literal>!=</literal> into
      <literal>!==</literal>. This is one of my favorite features to the
      language, and yet one of the most simple. What's the reasoning
      behind this? Well frankly JavaScript's type coercion is a bit odd,
      and its equality operator coerces types in order to compare them,
      leading to some confusing behaviors and the source of many bugs.
      There's a longer discussing on this topic in chapter 7.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>String interpolation</title>
    <para>
      CoffeeScript brings Ruby style string interpolation to JavaScript.
      Double quotes strings can contain <literal>#{}</literal> tags,
      which contain expressions to be interpolated into the string.
    </para>
    <screen>
favourite_color = "Blue. No, yel..."
question = "Bridgekeeper: What... is your favourite color?
            Galahad: #{favourite_color}
            Bridgekeeper: Wrong!
            "
</screen><para>Compiles down to:</para><screen>(function() {
  var favourite_color, question;

  favourite_color = "Blue. No, yel...";

  question = "Bridgekeeper: What... is your favourite color?            Galahad: " + favourite_color + "            Bridgekeeper: Wrong!            ";

}).call(this);
</screen>
    <para>
      As you can see in the example above, multiline strings are also
      allowed, without having to prefix each line with a
      <literal>+</literal>.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Loops and Comprehensions</title>
    <para>
      Array iteration in JavaScript has a rather archaic syntax,
      reminiscent of an older language like C rather than a modern
      object orientated one. The introduction of ES5 improved that
      situation somewhat, with the <literal>forEach()</literal>
      function, but that still requires a function call every iteration
      and is therefore much slower. Again, CoffeeScript comes to the
      rescue, with a beautiful syntax:
    </para>
    <screen>
for name in ["Roger", "Roderick", "Brian"]
  alert "Release #{name}"
</screen><para>Compiles down to:</para><screen>(function() {
  var name, _i, _len, _ref;

  _ref = ["Roger", "Roderick", "Brian"];
  for (_i = 0, _len = _ref.length; _i &lt; _len; _i++) {
    name = _ref[_i];
    alert("Release " + name);
  }

}).call(this);
</screen>
    <para>
      If you need the current iteration index, just pass an extra
      argument:
    </para>
    <screen>
for name, i in ["Roger the pickpocket", "Roderick the robber"]
  alert "#{i} - Release #{name}"
</screen><para>Compiles down to:</para><screen>(function() {
  var i, name, _len, _ref;

  _ref = ["Roger the pickpocket", "Roderick the robber"];
  for (i = 0, _len = _ref.length; i &lt; _len; i++) {
    name = _ref[i];
    alert("" + i + " - Release " + name);
  }

}).call(this);
</screen>
    <para>
      You can also iterate on one line, using the postfix form.
    </para>
    <screen>
release prisoner for prisoner in ["Roger", "Roderick", "Brian"]
</screen><para>Compiles down to:</para><screen>(function() {
  var prisoner, _i, _len, _ref;

  _ref = ["Roger", "Roderick", "Brian"];
  for (_i = 0, _len = _ref.length; _i &lt; _len; _i++) {
    prisoner = _ref[_i];
    release(prisoner);
  }

}).call(this);
</screen>
    <para>
      As with Python comprehensions, you can filter them:
    </para>
    <screen>
prisoners = ["Roger", "Roderick", "Brian"]
release prisoner for prisoner in prisoners when prisoner[0] is "R" 
</screen><para>Compiles down to:</para><screen>(function() {
  var prisoner, prisoners, _i, _len;

  prisoners = ["Roger", "Roderick", "Brian"];

  for (_i = 0, _len = prisoners.length; _i &lt; _len; _i++) {
    prisoner = prisoners[_i];
    if (prisoner[0] === "R") release(prisoner);
  }

}).call(this);
</screen>
    <para>
      You can also use comprehensions for iterating over properties in
      objects. Instead of the <literal>in</literal> keyword, use
      <literal>of</literal>.
    </para>
    <screen>
names = sam: seaborn, donna: moss
alert("#{first} #{last}") for first, last of names
</screen><para>Compiles down to:</para><screen>(function() {
  var first, last, names;

  names = {
    sam: seaborn,
    donna: moss
  };

  for (first in names) {
    last = names[first];
    alert("" + first + " " + last);
  }

}).call(this);
</screen>
    <para>
      The only low-level loop that CoffeeScript exposes is the
      <literal>while</literal> loop. This has similar behavior to the
      <literal>while</literal> loop in pure JavaScript, but has the
      added advantage that it returns an array of results, i.e. like the
      <literal>Array.prototype.map()</literal> function.
    </para>
    <screen>
num = 6
minstrel = while num -= 1
  num + " Brave Sir Robin ran away"
</screen><para>Compiles down to:</para><screen>(function() {
  var minstrel, num;

  num = 6;

  minstrel = (function() {
    var _results;
    _results = [];
    while (num -= 1) {
      _results.push(num + " Brave Sir Robin ran away");
    }
    return _results;
  })();

}).call(this);
</screen>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Arrays</title>
    <para>
      CoffeeScript takes inspiration from Ruby when it comes to array
      slicing by using ranges. Ranges are created by two numerical
      values, the first and last positions in the range, separated by
      <literal>..</literal> or <literal>...</literal>. If a range isn't
      prefixed by anything, CoffeeScript expands it out into an array.
    </para>
    <screen>
range = [1..5]
</screen><para>Compiles down to:</para><screen>(function() {
  var range;

  range = [1, 2, 3, 4, 5];

}).call(this);
</screen>
    <para>
      If, however, the range is specified immediately after a variable,
      CoffeeScript converts it into a <literal>slice()</literal> method
      call.
    </para>
    <screen>
firstTwo = ["one", "two", "three"][0..1]
</screen><para>Compiles down to:</para><screen>(function() {
  var firstTwo;

  firstTwo = ["one", "two", "three"].slice(0, 2);

}).call(this);
</screen>
    <para>
      In the example above, the range returns a new array, containing
      only the first two elements of the original array. You can also
      use the same syntax for replacing an array segment with another
      array.
    </para>
    <screen>
numbers = [0..9]
numbers[3..5] = [-3, -4, -5]
</screen><para>Compiles down to:</para><screen>(function() {
  var numbers, _ref;

  numbers = [0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9];

  [].splice.apply(numbers, [3, 3].concat(_ref = [-3, -4, -5])), _ref;

}).call(this);
</screen>
    <para>
      What's neat, is that JavaScript allows you to call
      <literal>slice()</literal> on strings too, so you can use ranges
      with string to return a new subset of characters.
    </para>
    <screen>
my = "my string"[0..2]
</screen><para>Compiles down to:</para><screen>(function() {
  var my;

  my = "my string".slice(0, 3);

}).call(this);
</screen>
    <para>
      Checking to see if a value exists inside an array is always a bore
      in JavaScript, particular as <literal>indexOf()</literal> doesn't
      yet have full cross-browser support (IE, I'm talking about you).
      CoffeeScript solves this with the <literal>in</literal> operator,
      for example.
    </para>
    <screen>
words = ["rattled", "roudy", "rebbles", "ranks"]
alert "Stop wagging me" if "ranks" in words 
</screen><para>Compiles down to:</para><screen>(function() {
  var words;
  var __hasProp = Object.prototype.hasOwnProperty, __indexOf = Array.prototype.indexOf || function(item) { for (var i = 0, l = this.length; i &lt; l; i++) { if (__hasProp.call(this, i) &amp;&amp; this[i] === item) return i; } return -1; };

  words = ["rattled", "roudy", "rebbles", "ranks"];

  if (__indexOf.call(words, "ranks") &gt;= 0) alert("Stop wagging me");

}).call(this);
</screen>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Aliases &amp; the Existential Operator</title>
    <para>
      CoffeeScript includes some useful aliases to save some typing. One
      of which is <literal>@</literal>, which is an alias for
      <literal>this</literal>.
    </para>
    <screen>
@saviour = true
</screen><para>Compiles down to:</para><screen>
  this.saviour = true;
</screen>
    <para>
      Another is <literal>::</literal>, which is an alias for
      <literal>prototype</literal>
    </para>
    <screen>
User::first = -&gt; @records[0]
</screen><para>Compiles down to:</para><screen>
  User.prototype.first = function() {
    return this.records[0];
  };
</screen>
    <para>
      Using <literal>if</literal> for <literal>null</literal> checks in
      JavaScript is common, but has a few pitfalls in that empty strings
      and zero are both coerced into <literal>false</literal>, which can
      catch you out. CoffeeScript existential operator
      <literal>?</literal> returns true unless a variable is
      <literal>null</literal> or <literal>undefined</literal>, similar
      to Ruby's <literal>nil?</literal>.
    </para>
    <screen>
praise if brian?
</screen><para>Compiles down to:</para><screen>
  if (typeof brian !== "undefined" &amp;&amp; brian !== null) praise;
</screen>
    <para>
      You can also use it in place of the <literal>||</literal>
      operator:
    </para>
    <screen>
velocity = southern ? 40
</screen><para>Compiles down to:</para><screen>(function() {
  var velocity;

  velocity = typeof southern !== "undefined" &amp;&amp; southern !== null ? southern : 40;

}).call(this);
</screen>
    <para>
      If you're using a <literal>null</literal> check before accessing a
      property, you can skip that by placing the existential operator
      right before it. This is similar to Active Support's
      <ulink url="http://guides.rubyonrails.org/active_support_core_extensions.html#try"><literal>try</literal></ulink>
      method.
    </para>
    <screen>
blackKnight.getLegs()?.kick()
</screen><para>Compiles down to:</para><screen>(function() {
  var _ref;

  if ((_ref = blackKnight.getLegs()) != null) _ref.kick();

}).call(this);
</screen>
    <para>
      Similarly you can check that a property is actually a function,
      and callable, by placing the existential operator right before the
      parens. If the property doesn't exist, or isn't a function, it
      simply won't get called.
    </para>
    <screen>
blackKnight.getLegs().kick?()
</screen><para>Compiles down to:</para><screen>(function() {
  var _base;

  if (typeof (_base = blackKnight.getLegs()).kick === "function") _base.kick();

}).call(this);
</screen>
  </sect1>


</chapter>