<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter>
<title>Classes</title>
 <sect1>
  <title>Classes</title>
  <para>
    Classes in JavaScript seem to have the kind of effect that cloves of
    garlic have to Dracula for some purists; although, let's be honest,
    if you're that way inclined, you're unlikely to be reading a book on
    CoffeeScript. However, it turns out that classes are just as damn
    useful in JavaScript as they are in other languages and CoffeeScript
    provides a great abstraction.
  </para>
  <para>
    Behind the scenes, CoffeeScript is using JavaScript's native
    prototype to create classes; adding a bit of syntactic sugar for
    static property inheritance and context persistence. As a developer
    all that's exposed to you is the <literal>class</literal> keyword.
  </para>
  <screen>
//= CoffeeScript
class Animal
</screen>
  <para>
    In the example above, <literal>Animal</literal> is the name of the
    class, and also the name of the resultant variable that you can use
    to create instances. Behind the scenes CoffeeScript is using
    constructor functions, which means you can instantiate classes using
    the <literal>new</literal> operator.
  </para>
  <screen>
//= CoffeeScript
animal = new Animal
</screen>
  <para>
    Defining constructors (functions that get invoked upon
    instantiation) is simple, just use a function named
    <literal>constructor</literal>. This is akin to using Ruby's
    <literal>initialize</literal> or Python's
    <literal>__init__</literal>.
  </para>
  <screen>
//= CoffeeScript
class Animal
  constructor: (name) -&gt;
    @name = name
</screen>
  <para>
    In fact, CoffeeScript provides a shorthand for the common pattern of
    setting instance properties. By prefixing argument's with
    <literal>@</literal>, CoffeeScript will automatically set the
    arguments as instance properties in the constructor. Indeed, this
    shorthand will also work for normal functions outside classes. The
    example below is equivalent to the last example, where we set the
    instance properties manually.
  </para>
  <screen>
//= CoffeeScript
class Animal
  constructor: (@name) -&gt;
</screen>
  <para>
    As you'd expect, any arguments passed on instantiation are proxied
    to the constructor function.
  </para>
  <screen>
//= CoffeeScript
animal = new Animal("Parrot")
alert "Animal is a #{animal.name}"
</screen>
  <sect2>
    <title>Instance properties</title>
    <para>
      Adding additional instance properties to a class is very
      straightforward, it's exactly the syntax as adding properties onto
      an object. Just make sure properties are indented correctly inside
      the class body.
    </para>
    <screen>
//= CoffeeScript
class Animal
  price: 5

  sell: (customer) -&gt;

animal = new Animal
animal.sell(new Customer)
</screen>
    <para>
      Context changes are rife within JavaScript, and earlier in the
      Syntax chapter we talked about how CoffeeScript can lock the value
      of <literal>this</literal> to a particular context using a fat
      arrow function: <literal>=&gt;</literal>. This ensures that
      whatever context a function is called under, it'll always execute
      inside the context it was created in. CoffeeScript has extended
      support for fat arrows to classes, so by using a fat arrow for an
      instance method you'll ensure that it's invoked in the correct
      context, and that <literal>this</literal> is always equal to the
      current instance.
    </para>
    <screen>
//= CoffeeScript
class Animal
  price: 5

  sell: =&gt;
    alert "Give me #{@price} shillings!"

animal = new Animal
$("#sell").click(animal.sell)
</screen>
    <para>
      As demonstrated in the example above, this is especially useful in
      event callbacks. Normally the <literal>sell()</literal> function
      would be invoked in the context of the <literal>#sell</literal>
      element. However, by using fat arrows for
      <literal>sell()</literal>, we're ensuring the correct context is
      being maintained, and that <literal>this.price</literal> equals
      <literal>5</literal>.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
    <title>Static properties</title>
    <para>
      How about defining class (i.e. static) properties? Well, it turns
      out that inside a class definition, <literal>this</literal> refers
      to the class object. In other words you can set class properties
      by setting them directly on <literal>this</literal>.
    </para>
    <screen>
//= CoffeeScript
class Animal
  this.find = (name) -&gt;      

Animal.find("Parrot")
</screen>
    <para>
      In fact, as you may remember, CoffeeScript aliases
      <literal>this</literal> to <literal>@</literal>, which lets you
      write static properties even more succinctly:
    </para>
    <screen>
//= CoffeeScript
class Animal
  @find: (name) -&gt;

Animal.find("Parrot")
</screen>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
    <title>Inheritance &amp; Super</title>
    <para>
      It wouldn't be a proper class implementation without some form of
      inheritance, and CoffeeScript doesn't disappoint. You can inherit
      from another class by using the <literal>extends</literal>
      keyword. In the example below, <literal>Parrot</literal> extends
      from <literal>Animal</literal>, inheriting all of its instance
      properties, such as <literal>alive()</literal>
    </para>
    <screen>
//= CoffeeScript
class Animal
  constructor: (@name) -&gt;

  alive: -&gt;
    false

class Parrot extends Animal
  constructor: -&gt;
    super("Parrot")

  dead: -&gt;
    not @alive()
</screen>
    <para>
      You'll notice that in the example above, we're using the
      <literal>super()</literal> keyword. Behind the scenes, this is
      translated into a function call on the class' parent prototype,
      invoked in the current context. In this case, it'll be
      <literal>Parrot.__super__.constructor.call(this, "Parrot");</literal>.
      In practice, this will have exactly the same effect as invoking
      <literal>super</literal> in Ruby or Python, invoking the
      overridden inherited function.
    </para>
    <para>
      Unless you override the <literal>constructor</literal>, by default
      CoffeeScript will invoke the parent's constructor when instances
      are created.
    </para>
    <para>
      CoffeeScript uses prototypal inheritance to automatically inherit
      all of a class's instance properties. This ensures that classes
      are dynamic; even if you add properties to a parent class after a
      child has been created, the property will still be propagated to
      all of its inherited children.
    </para>
    <screen>
//= CoffeeScript
class Animal
  constructor: (@name) -&gt;

class Parrot extends Animal

Animal::rip = true

parrot = new Parrot("Macaw")
alert("This parrot is no more") if parrot.rip
</screen>
    <para>
      It's worth pointing out though that static properties are copied
      to subclasses, rather than inherited using prototype as instance
      properties are. This is due to implementation details with
      JavaScript's prototypal architecture, and is a difficult problem
      to work around.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
    <title>Mixins</title>
    <para>
      <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mixin">Mixins</ulink> are
      not something supported natively by CoffeeScript, for the good
      reason that they can be trivially implemented yourself. For
      example, here's two functions, <literal>extend()</literal> and
      <literal>include()</literal> that'll add class and instance
      properties respectively to a class.
    </para>
    <screen>
//= CoffeeScript
extend = (obj, mixin) -&gt;
  obj[name] = method for name, method of mixin        
  obj

include = (klass, mixin) -&gt;
  extend klass.prototype, mixin

# Usage
include Parrot,
  isDeceased: true

(new Parrot).isDeceased
</screen>
    <para>
      Mixins are a great pattern for sharing common logic between
      modules when inheritance is not suited. The advantage of mixins,
      is that you can include multiple ones, compared to inheritance
      where only one class can be inherited from.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
    <title>Extending classes</title>
    <para>
      Mixins are pretty neat, but they're not very object orientated.
      Instead, let's integrate mixins into CoffeeScript's classes. We're
      going to define a class called <literal>Module</literal> that we
      can inherit from for mixin support. <literal>Module</literal> will
      have two static functions, <literal>@extend()</literal> and
      <literal>@include()</literal> which we can use for extending the
      class with static and instance properties respectively.
    </para>
    <screen>
//= CoffeeScript
moduleKeywords = ['extended', 'included']

class Module
  @extend: (obj) -&gt;
    for key, value of obj when key not in moduleKeywords
      @[key] = value

    obj.extended?.apply(@)
    this

  @include: (obj) -&gt;
    for key, value of obj when key not in moduleKeywords
      # Assign properties to the prototype
      @::[key] = value

    obj.included?.apply(@)
    this
</screen>
    <para>
      The little dance around the <literal>moduleKeywords</literal>
      variable is to ensure we have callback support when mixins extend
      a class. Let's take a look at our <literal>Module</literal> class
      in action:
    </para>
    <screen>
//= CoffeeScript
classProperties = 
  find: (id) -&gt;
  create: (attrs) -&gt;

instanceProperties =
  save: -&gt; 

class User extends Module
  @extend classProperties
  @include instanceProperties

# Usage:
user = User.find(1)

user = new User
user.save()
</screen>
    <para>
      As you can see, we've added some static properties,
      <literal>find()</literal> and <literal>create()</literal> to the
      <literal>User</literal> class, as well as some instance
      properties, <literal>save()</literal>. Since we've got callbacks
      whenever modules are extended, we can shortcut the process of
      applying both static and instance properties:
    </para>
    <screen>
//= CoffeeScript
ORM = 
  find: (id) -&gt;
  create: (attrs) -&gt;
  extended: -&gt;
    @include
      save: -&gt; 

class User extends Module
  @extend ORM
</screen>
    <para>
      Super simple and elegant!
    </para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>

</chapter>