<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter>
<title>Common CoffeeScript idioms</title>
 
  
  <para>
    Every language has a set of idioms and practices, and CoffeeScript
    is no exception. This chapter will explore those conventions, and
    show you some JavaScript to CoffeeScript comparisons so you can get
    a practical sense of the language.
  </para>
  <sect1>
    <title>Each</title>
    <para>
      In JavaScript to iterate over every item in an array, we could
      either use the newly added
      <ulink url="https://developer.mozilla.org/en/JavaScript/Reference/Global_Objects/array/foreach"><literal>forEach()</literal></ulink>
      function, or an old C style <literal>for</literal> loop. If you're
      planning to use some of JavaScript's latest features introduced in
      ECMAScript 5, I advise you also include a
      <ulink url="https://github.com/kriskowal/es5-shim">shim</ulink> in
      the page to emulate support in older browsers.
    </para>
    <screen>
for (var i=0; i &lt; array.length; i++)
  myFunction(array[i]);

array.forEach(function(item, i){
  myFunction(item)
});
</screen>
    <para>
      Although the <literal>forEach()</literal> syntax is much more
      succinct and readable, it suffers from the drawback that the
      callback function will be invoked every iteration of the array,
      and is therefore much slower than the equivalent
      <literal>for</literal> loop. Let's see how it looks in
      CoffeeScript.
    </para>
    <screen>myFunction(item) for item in array
</screen>
    <para>
      It's a readable and concise syntax, I'm sure you'll agree, and
      what's great is that it compiles to a <literal>for</literal> loop
      behind the scenes. In other words CoffeeScript's syntax offers the
      same expressiveness as <literal>forEach()</literal>, but without
      the speed and shimming caveats.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Map</title>
    <para>
      As with <literal>forEach()</literal>, ES5 also includes a native
      map function that has a much more succinct syntax than the classic
      <literal>for</literal> loop, namely
      <ulink url="https://developer.mozilla.org/en/JavaScript/Reference/Global_Objects/Array/map"><literal>map()</literal></ulink>.
      Unfortunately it suffers from much the same caveats that
      <literal>forEach()</literal> does, its speed is greatly reduced
      due to the function calls.
    </para>
    <screen>
var result = []
for (var i=0; i &lt; array.length; i++)
  result.push(array[i].name)

var result = array.map(function(item, i){
  return item.name;
});
</screen>
    <para>
      As we covered in the syntax chapter, CoffeeScript's comprehensions
      can be used to get the same behavior as <literal>map()</literal>.
      Notice we're surrounding the comprehension with parens, which is
      <emphasis role="strong">absolutely critical</emphasis> in ensuring
      the comprehension returns what you'd expect, the mapped array.
    </para>
    <screen>result = (item.name for item in array)
</screen>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Select</title>
    <para>
      Again, ES5 has a utility function
      <ulink url="https://developer.mozilla.org/en/JavaScript/Reference/Global_Objects/array/filter"><literal>filter()</literal></ulink>
      for reducing arrays:
    </para>
    <screen>
var result = []
for (var i=0; i &lt; array.length; i++)
  if (array[i].name == "test")
    result.push(array[i])

result = array.filter(function(item, i){
  return item.name == "test"
});
</screen>
    <para>
      CoffeeScript's basic syntax uses the <literal>when</literal>
      keyword to filter items with a comparison. Behind the scenes a
      <literal>for</literal> loop is generated. The whole execution is
      performed in an anonymous function to ward against scope leakage
      and variable conflict.
    </para>
    <screen>result = (item for item in array when item.name is "test")
</screen>
    <para>
      Don't forgot to include the parens, as otherwise
      <literal>result</literal> will be the last item in the array.
      CoffeeScript's comprehensions are so flexible that they allow you
      to do powerful selections as in the following example:
    </para>
    <screen>passed = []
failed = []
(if score &gt; 60 then passed else failed).push score for score in [49, 58, 76, 82, 88, 90]

# Or
passed = (score for score in scores when score &gt; 60)
</screen>
    <para>
      If comprehensions get too long, you can split them onto multiple
      lines.
    </para>
    <screen>passed = []
failed = []
for score in [49, 58, 76, 82, 88, 90]
  (if score &gt; 60 then passed else failed).push score
</screen>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Includes</title>
    <para>
      Checking to see if a value is inside an array is typically done
      with <literal>indexOf()</literal>, which rather mind-bogglingly
      still requires a shim, as Internet Explorer hasn't implemented it.
    </para>
    <screen>
var included = (array.indexOf("test") != -1)
</screen>
    <para>
      CoffeeScript has a neat alternative to this which Pythonists may
      recognize, namely <literal>in</literal>.
    </para>
    <screen>
included = "test" in array
</screen>
    <para>
      Behind the scenes, CoffeeScript is using
      <literal>Array.prototype.indexOf()</literal>, and shimming if
      necessary, to detect if the value is inside the array.
      Unfortunately this means the same <literal>in</literal> syntax
      won't work for strings. We need to revert back to using
      <literal>indexOf()</literal> and testing if the result is
      negative:
    </para>
    <screen>included = "a long test string".indexOf("test") isnt -1
</screen>
    <para>
      Or even better, hijack the bitwise operator so we don't have to do
      a <literal>-1</literal> comparison.
    </para>
    <screen>string   = "a long test string"
included = !!~ string.indexOf "test"
</screen>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Property iteration</title>
    <para>
      To iterate over a bunch of properties in JavaScript, you'd use the
      <literal>in</literal> operator, for example:
    </para>
    <screen>
var object = {one: 1, two: 2}
for(var key in object) alert(key + " = " + object[key])
</screen>
    <para>
      However, as you've seen in the previous section, CoffeeScript has
      already reserved <literal>in</literal> for use with arrays.
      Instead, the operator has been renamed <literal>of</literal>, and
      can be used like thus:
    </para>
    <screen>
//= CoffeeScript    
object = {one: 1, two: 2}
alert("#{key} = #{value}") for key, value of object
</screen>
    <para>
      As you can see, you can specify variables for both the property
      name, and its value; rather convenient.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Min/Max</title>
    <para>
      This technique is not specific to CoffeeScript, but I thought it
      useful to demonstrate anyway. <literal>Math.max</literal> and
      <literal>Math.min</literal> take multiple arguments, so you can
      easily use <literal>...</literal> to pass an array to them,
      retrieving the maximum and minimum values in the array.
    </para>
    <screen>Math.max [14, 35, -7, 46, 98]... # 98
Math.min [14, 35, -7, 46, 98]... # -7
</screen>
    <para>
      It's worth noting that this trick will fail with really large
      arrays as browsers have a limitation on the amount of arguments
      you can pass to functions.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Multiple arguments</title>
    <para>
      In the <literal>Math.max</literal> example above, we're using
      <literal>...</literal> to de-structure the array and passing it as
      multiple arguments to <literal>max</literal>. Behind the scenes,
      CoffeeScript is converting the function call to use
      <literal>apply()</literal>, ensuring the array is passed as
      multiple arguments to <literal>max</literal>. We can use this
      feature in other ways too, such as proxying function calls:
    </para>
    <screen>Log =
  log: -&gt;
    console?.log(arguments...)
</screen>
    <para>
      Or you can alter the arguments before they're passed onwards:
    </para>
    <screen>Log =
  logPrefix: "(App)"

  log: (args...) -&gt;
    args.unshift(@logPrefix) if @logPrefix
    console?.log(args...)
</screen>
    <para>
      Bear in mind though, that CoffeeScript will automatically set the
      function invocation context to the object the function is being
      invoked on. In the example above, that would be
      <literal>console</literal>. If you want to set the context
      specifically, then you'll need to call <literal>apply()</literal>
      manually.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>And/or</title>
    <para>
      CoffeeScript style guides indicates that <literal>or</literal> is
      preferred over <literal>||</literal>, and <literal>and</literal>
      is preferred over <literal>&amp;&amp;</literal>. I can see why, as
      the former is somewhat more readable. Nevertheless, the two styles
      have identical results.
    </para>
    <para>
      This preference over more English style code also applies to using
      <literal>is</literal> over <literal>==</literal> and
      <literal>isnt</literal> over <literal>!=</literal>.
    </para>
    <screen>string = "migrating coconuts"
string == string # true
string is string # true
</screen>
    <para>
      One extremely nice addition to CoffeeScript is the 'or equals',
      which is a pattern Rubyists may recognize as
      <literal>||=</literal>:
    </para>
    <screen>hash or= {}
</screen>
    <para>
      If hash evaluates to <literal>false</literal>, then it's set to an
      empty object. It's important to note here that this expression
      also recognizes <literal>0</literal>,
      <literal>""</literal> and <literal>null</literal> as
      false. If that isn't your intention, you'll need to use
      CoffeeScript's existential operator, which only gets activated if
      <literal>hash</literal> is <literal>undefined</literal> or
      <literal>null</literal>:
    </para>
    <screen>hash ?= {}
</screen>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Destructuring assignments</title>
    <para>
      Destructuring assignments can be used with any depth of array and
      object nesting, to help pull out deeply nested properties.
    </para>
    <screen>someObject = { a: 'value for a', b: 'value for b' }
{ a, b } = someObject
console.log "a is '#{a}', b is '#{b}'"
</screen>
    <para>
      This is especially useful in Node applications when requiring
      modules:
    </para>
    <screen>{join, resolve} = require('path')

join('/Users', 'Alex')
</screen>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>External libraries</title>
    <para>
      Using external libraries is exactly the same as calling functions
      on CoffeeScript libraries; since at the end of the day everything
      is compiled down to JavaScript. Using CoffeeScript with
      <ulink url="http://jquery.com">jQuery</ulink> is especially
      elegant, due to the amount of callbacks in jQuery's API.
    </para>
    <screen># Use local alias
$ = jQuery

$ -&gt;
  # DOMContentLoaded
  $(".el").click -&gt;
    alert("Clicked!")
</screen>
    <para>
      Since all of CoffeeScript's output is wrapped in an anonymous
      function, we can set a local <literal>$</literal> alias for
      <literal>jQuery</literal>. This will make sure that even if
      jQuery's no conflict mode is enabled and the <literal>$</literal>
      re-defined, our script will still function as intended.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Private variables</title>
    <para>
      The <literal>do</literal> keyword in CoffeeScript lets us execute
      functions immediately, a great way of encapsulating scope &amp;
      protecting variables. In the example below, we're defining a
      variable <literal>classToType</literal> in the context of an
      anonymous function which's immediately called by
      <literal>do</literal>. That anonymous function returns a second
      anonymous function, which will be ultimate value of
      <literal>type</literal>. Since <literal>classToType</literal> is
      defined in a context that no reference is kept to, it can't be
      accessed outside that scope.
    </para>
    <screen># Execute function immediately
type = do -&gt;
  classToType = {}
  for name in "Boolean Number String Function Array Date RegExp Undefined Null".split(" ")
    classToType["[object " + name + "]"] = name.toLowerCase()

  # Return a function
  (obj) -&gt;
    strType = Object::toString.call(obj)
    classToType[strType] or "object"
</screen>
    <para>
      In other words, <literal>classToType</literal> is completely
      private, and can never again be referenced outside the executing
      anonymous function. This pattern is a great way of encapsulating
      scope and hiding variables.
    </para>
  </sect1>


</chapter>